Guide to the Norman Foerster Papers, 1907-1965
Department of Special Collections
Norman Foerster Papers,
1907-1965
Special Collections M0183
Foerster, Norman, 1887-
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted: requires 24 hr. paging period.
Provenance
Gift of Norman Foerster, 1969.
Access Terms
Adams, R. P.; Allen, Francis Henry, 1866-; Baker, Joseph E.; Ball, John.; Beach, Joseph Warren, 1880-1957.; Bill, Earl Gordon, 1884-; Bowling, Lawrence.; Bradford, Gamaliel, 1863-1932.; Brooks, Cleanth, 1906-; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; Brown, Margaret.; Bush, Douglas, 1896-; Campbell, Oscar James, 1879-1970.; Canby, Henry Seidel, 1878-1961.; Cather, Willa, 1873-1947.; Chadsey, C. P.; Chalmers, Gordon K.; Chapman, Warren.; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1887-; Coffey, Hubert Stanley.; Conrath, John.; Coyle, William.; Crane, Ronald Salmon, 1886-; Davies, Graham R.; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965.; Elliot, William Foster.; Elliot, George Roy, 1883-1963.; Elton, Oliver, 1861-1945.; Falk, Robert.; Foerster, Donald.; Foerster, Norman, 1887-; Gauss, Christian Frederick, 1878-1951.; Gohdes, Clarence Louis Frank, 1901-; Goldberg, Maxwell Henry, 1907-; Goodell, Charles E., Mrs.; Greene, Theodore M.; Gu erard, Albert L eon, 1880-1959.; Guttman, Allen.; Hart, James David, 1911-; Havens, Raymond Dexter, 1880-; Hicks, Philip M.; Howarth, Herbert.; Howe, W. D.; Hubbell, Jay Broadus, 1885-; Jaeger, Wernes Wilhelm, 1888-1961.; Jessup, Walter Albert, 1877-; Jones, Harry Stuart Veddes, 1878-; Kelly, Robert, 1935-; Kilpatrick, William Heard, 1871-1965.; Kirby, Thomas A.; Lambert, John S.; Livingstone, Richard Winn, Sir, 1880-1960.; Long, Percy Waldron, 1876-; L udeke, H.; Mc Grath, Earl James, 1902-; McNeill, Louise.; Meiklejohn, Alexander, 1872-1964.; Moore, C. A.; More, Paul Elmer, 1864-1937.; Murry, John Middleton, 1889-1957.; Parkman, Francis.; Quinn, Arhtur Hobson, 1875-1960.; Rafton, Harold R.; Ramsay, Robert L.; Reilly, Robert James, 1925-; Robinson, Frederick.; Rulard, Richard, 1932-; Ryan, Alfred S.; Sandeen, Ernest Emanual, 1908-; Schneider, W. B.; Seldes, Gilbert Vivian, 1893-; Shapiro, Karl Jay, 1913-; Slote, Bernice.; Smith, D. Michel.; Spilles, Robert Ernest, 1896-; Spring, Samuel, 1746-1819.; Stevens, David H., 1860-; Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955.; Stiles, Lindley Joseph, 1913-; Stokowska, Evangeline.; Stroud, J. B.; Stung, Arthur, N.; Su, Wei-Hsiung.; Van Doren, Carl, 1885-1950.; Wellek, Ren e.; Ferrar and Rinehart, Inc.; Houghton Mifflin Company.; Macmillan Company.; University of Iowa.
Container List
- Section I: Works By Norman Foerster.
  - Address given to the Rotary Club of Montecito, California, March 3, 1953,ts., 5 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Ideals and the Annihilation Of Germany, ts., 5pp., written c. 1914 - 1917. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Literature, carbon ts., 23pp., written for the World Book Encyclopedia. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Irving Babbitt, carbon ts., 3 pp., written for The Dictionary Of American Biography. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fragment on Irving Babbitt, autograph manuscript, 8 pp. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biography Of Thoreau, fragment never completed, ts., 16 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John Burroughs, carbon ts., 13 pp., written for The Dictionary Of American Biography. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Essays and notes written while Foerster was at Harvard College, 1907 - 1910,(20), including a bound ts. of poems, Spring and Fall, 1907;and an essay on The Influence Of Gilbert White, which received the first Bowdoin Prize ever awarded (1910). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - East Of San Francisco, ts., 10 pp. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fascism, ts., 3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Education In Literature, ts. of unpublished book, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Goethe and the Humanist Movement In America, ts., 25 pp. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Has Science Advanced Human Happiness?, ts., 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Man Unveils Me, carbon ts., 14 pp. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Metamorphosis, ts., 5 pp. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Naturalism, as revised 1943 - 1944,ts., 26 pp., and carbon, 24 pp., (pages 25 - 26 of the carbon are missing). (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rousseau and Romanticism by Irving Babbitt, a review, autograph ms., 9 pp. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Some Ways Of Studying Literature, ts., 15 pp. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Toward Socialism, ts., 8 pp. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The United States In the World, outline, ts., 6pp. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - What Is a Good Teacher Of Literature?, ts., 18 pp. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Radio Interview, transcript, December 4, 1942,ts., 9 pp. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes, Miscellaneous. c. 1920 - 1961, (c. 100 items). (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - HUMANITIES AND THE COMMON MAN -JAPANESE EDITION [UNK] DATA ON PUBLICATION (Folder 23a)
- Section II: Works by persons other than Norman Foerster.
  - Miscellaneous, 1929 - 1930(13), including a poem by Robert Frost with autograph correction. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Eliot, T. S., critical notes on Foerster's Of Culture and Religion In America, autograph ms., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Papers by students of Foerster, (9). (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Papers by students of Foerster (Box 2, Folder 26a)
- Section III: Correspondence.
  (Dates outside parentheses indicate inclusive dates of letters in file; numbers in parentheses indicate number of items in file.)
  - General File, including letters to, from, or about, the following: (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Unidentified, crank mail, and miscellaneous, (21).
    - Adams, R. P., 1952.
    - Allen, Francis Henry (1866 -) 1923.
    - The American Scholar, correspondence occasioned by the publication of; See Folder 2 - 28.
    - Baker, Joseph E. 1963.
    - Ball, John, 1958.
    - Beach, Joseph Warren, 1946.
    - Bill, Earl Gordon (1884 -); See Folder 2 - 30.
    - Bowling, Lawrence, 1957 - 1958, (3).
    - Bradford, Gamaliel (1863 - 1932) 1923.
    - Brooks, Cleanth, 1945.
    - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1920.
    - Brown, Margaret, n.d.
    - Bush, Douglas, 1967.
    - Campbell, Oscar James (1879 -) 1919.
    - Canby, Henry Seidel (1878 -); See Folder 2 - 28.
    - Cather, Willa (1873 - 1947); See Folder 2- 29.
    - Chadsey, C. P., 1944.
    - Chalmers, Gordon K., 1944.
    - Chapman, Warren, 1951, (2).
    - Chase, Harry Woodburn (1887 -); See Folder 2 - 28.
    - Coffey, Hubert Stanley, 1944.
    - Commission On Liberal Education, 1947.
    - Conrath, John, 1961 - 1966, (4).
    - Coyle, William, 1958, (2).
    - Crane, Ronald Salmon (1886 -) 1935.
    - Davies, G. R., 1943, (2).
    - Education Leads the Way, correspondence occasioned by the publication of; See Folder 2 - 30.
    - Elliot, William Foster, 1923.
    - Elliot, G. R., 1945.
    - Elton, Oliver (1861 -) 1921 - 1930(2); See also Folder 2 - 28.
    - Fact Bureau, 1946.
    - Falk, Robert, 1961.
    - Ferrar and Rinehart, Inc., publishers, 1930.
    - Foerster, Donald, 1957.
    - Foerster, Norman, n.d., 1955, (2).
    - Gauss, Christian (1878 -); See A University Prepared For Victory, file in this folder, and see also Folder 2 - 30.
    - Gohdes, Clarence Louis Frank (1901 -), 1964.
    - Goldberg, Maxwell, 1959.
    - Goodell, Mrs. Charles E., 1944.
    - Greene, Theodore M., 1947, (2).
    - Guerard, Albert Leon (1880 -) 1931.
    - Guttmann, Allen, 1965.
    - Hart, James D., 1959.
    - Havens, Raymond Dexter (1880 -) 1923.
    - Hicks, Philip M., 1951.
    - Houghton, Mifflin, Co., 1922 - 1947, (3).
    - Howarth, Herbert, 1960.
    - Howe, W. D., 1919.
    - Hubbell, Jay B., n.d.
    - Iowa, University Of. Archives. 1967, (2).
    - Iowa, University Of. Curriculum Reform Controversy; See Folder 2 - 31.
    - Iowa, University Of. News Service, 1930, (2).
    - Jaeger, Werner, 1942.
    - Jessup, Walter Albert (1877 -) n.d.;See also A University Prepared For Victory, file in this folder.
    - Jones, Harry Stuart Vedder (1878 -) 1935.
    - Kelly, Robert, 1962.
    - Kilpatrick, William Heard; See Folder 2 - 30.
    - Kirby, Thomas A., 1952.
    - Lambert, John S., 1961 - 1967, (3).
    - Literary Scholarship, correspondence occasioned by the publication of; See Folder 2 - 32.
    - Livingstone, R. W., n.d.
    - Long, Percy Waldron (1876 -) 1935.
    - Lüdeke, H., 1952.
    - McGrath, Earl James (1902 -) 1946.
    - Macmillan Company, 1923, (4).
    - McNeill, Louise, 1942.
    - Meiklejohn, Alexander (1872 -); See Folder 2 - 30.
    - Moore, C. A., n.d.
    - More, Paul Elmer (1864 - 1937); See Folder 2 - 33.
    - Murry, J. Middleton, 1923.
    - The New Republic, 1922.
    - North American Review, 1920.
    - Parkman, Francis Jr., 1959.
    - Quinn, Arthur H., 1932.
    - Rafton, Harold R., 1947.
    - Ramsay, Robert L., 1919.
    - Reilly, R. J., 1968.
    - Robinson, Frederick, 1933.
    - Ruland, Richard, 1957.
    - Ryan, Alfred S., 1960.
    - Sandeen, Ernest, n.d.
    - Schneider, W. B., 1957.
    - Seldes, Gilbert Vivian (1893 -) 1922.
    - Sewanee Review, 1920.
    - Shapiro, Karl Jay (1913 -) n.d.
    - Slote, Bernice, 1961, (2).
    - Smith, D. Michel, 1923.
    - South Atlantic Quarterly, n.d.
    - Spiller, Robert E., 1943 - 1966, (2).
    - Spring, Samuel, n.d.
    - Stevens, David H., (1860 -) 1947, (5).
    - Stevens, Wallace (1879 -) 1945.
    - Stiles, Lindley J., 1958.
    - Stokowska, Evangeline (Mrs. Leopold Stokowski); See Folder 2 -30.
    - Stroud, J. B., 1944.
    - Stunz, Arthur N, 1966 - 1967, (2).
    - Su, Wei-Hsiung, 1952.
    - A University Prepared For Victory, correspondence occasioned by the publication of, 1943, (24).
    - Van Doren, Carl (1885 -) 1920.
    - Wellek, René (1903 -) 1942 - 1967, (9).
  - Correspondence occasioned by the publication of the American Scholar, 1929,(54) including letters to, from, or about: (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Canby, Henry Seidel (1878 -) tls., 10/28/29.
    - Chase, Harry Woodburn (1887 -) tls., 10/4/29.
    - Elton, Oliver (1861 -) tls., 10/24/29.
  - Cather, Willa (1873 - 1947) tls., March 8, 1923. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Letters occasioned by the publication of Education Leads the Way, 1933,(13) including letters to and from: (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Bill, Earl Gordon (1884 -).
    - Gauss, Christian (1878 -).
    - Kilpatrick, William Heard (1871 -).
    - Meiklejohn, Alexander (1872 -).
    - Stokowska, Evangeline (Mrs. Leopold Stokowski).
  - University of Iowa, curriculum reofrm controversy; including correspondence (26), minutes of the University Of Iowa Steering Committee (6), newspaper clippings (5), and notes (22). A larger group of similar material was sent by Mr. Foerster to the Archives of the University Of Iowa in the early 1960's. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letters occasioned by the publication of Literary Scholarship, (23), 1941 - 1943. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - More, Paul Elmer (1864 - 1937) als., 3/13/23. (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Section IV: Documents. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - One folder, including:
    - Certificate of Doctorate Of Humane Letters, Grinnell College, June 10, 1946.
    - Certificate of membership in Phi Beta Kappa Society, given honoris causa at Duke University, March 21, 1949.
    - Contract for the publication of Toward Standards, with Ferrar, and Rinehart, June 30, 1930.
  - Biographical data on Norman Foerster, (3). (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Section V: Photographs, (2). (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Section VI: Printed material.
  - Miscellaneous, (28), including: (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - University of Iowa Bulletins, (16)
    - University Of North Carolina Press notices, (2).
  - Tearsheets, undated, (24). (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1910 - 1919, (32). (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1920 - 1924, (21). (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1925 - 1934, (40). (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1935 - 1939, (27). (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1940 - 1945, (36). (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1946 - 1949, (32). (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Tearsheets and periodicals (whole numbers), 1950 - 1965, (26). (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated, 1910 - 1919,(c. 125). (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1920 - 1929, (101). (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930-1964,first folder, (c. 100). (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930-1964,second folder, (c. 100). (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Section VII: Material used in teaching.
  - Teaching notes and materials, miscellaneous. (c. 40). (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Lectures delivered by Norman Foerster. (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - The Education Of a Writer, n.d.,ts., 6 pp.
    - Emerson: The Crucial Years, University of Illinois, t.s. 25 pp, and ts., 20pp., two different drafts.
    - Goethe and Humanism, n.d.,ts., 24 pp.
    - The Humanitarian Illusion, University of Nebraska, n.d.,carbon ts., 22 pp.
    - The New Pilgrim's Progress, n.d.,ts., 9 pp.
    - The Unity Of Europe, n.d.,carbon t.s., and ts. 4 pp.; ts., 6 pp.; ts., 4 pp.; three different drafts.
    - Whitman: The Crucial Years, University Of Illinois, n.d.,ts., 25pp.; ts., 19 pp.; two different drafts.
    - What Is a Good Teacher Of Literature? English Conference, Iowa City, October, 1930,ts., 15 pp.
    - Goethe and Humane Letters Today, Sewanee, March 20, 1931,ts., 21 pp.; Also delivered at Grinnell College, Fall, 1931;and at the University of Cincinnati, November 1932.
    - Philosophy and Literature, Philosophical Club, January 12, 1932,ts., 22 pp.
    - American Culture and the European, Modern Language Conference, March 5, 1932,ts., 10 pp.
    - Creating An Unknown Future, October 1932,carbon ts., 24 pp.
    - The Future of the Classics, Classical Conference, February 10, 1933,ts., 7 pp.
    - The Next Step, Iowa College Conference, February 16, 1935,carbon ts., 10 pp.
    - Thomas Jefferson- Freedom v. Regimentation, August 20, 1936.
    - The Heart Of the Curriculum, Federation of Illinois Colleges, February 19, 1937,carbon ts., 12 pp.
    - Untitled, St. Louis, February 14, 1939,carbon ts., 5 pp.; ts., 5 pp.; carbon ts., 4 pp.; three different drafts.
    - English In General Education, Raleigh, November 20, 1945,carbon ts., 6 pp.
    - Fine Arts For All, Ripon College, October 29, 1947,ts. and cts., 14 pp.
    - The Context Of Literary Scholarship Today, Philological Club, December 2, 1947,ts., 18 pp.
    - American Literature and World Leadership, William and Mary College, March 13, 1948,ts., and cts., 16 pp.
    - Wanted: A New Literary Movement, Pittsburgh, May 14, 1948,ts., 2 pp.
    - What Can Literature and the Arts Do For Us Today? North Carolina College, Durham, December 13, 1948,ts. 9 pp.
    - Recent Developments In American Literary History and Criticism, Friend of the Library, Santa Barbara, 11/15/54,ts., and cts., 16pp
  - Wordsworth material used by Foerster in teaching English 117 at Duke University, 1950;typescript and notes, including items on the following: (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Biographical data on Wordsworth.
    - Evening Walk.
    - Michael and Wordsworth's Ethics.
    - Ode: Intimations of Immortality.
    - The Prelude.
    - Fragment of The Recluse.
    - Sonnets of 1802.
    - Tintern Abbey
    - Dorothy Wordsworth.
Norman Foerster Papers
- Personal Correspondence
  - Jean Roberts - Daughter-in-law. Letters range from nov'68 - Sept'69. Concerning will, financial problems and personal misc. Also replies from Dr. [UNK]. (Folder folder I)
  - Correspondence with wife concerning divorce, also from niece (Folder folder II)
  - David Foerster - Son. Ranging from May '69 - Jun, '72. Concerning financial difficulties with father and personal misc. (Folder folder III)
  - Barrett Foerster - grandson - Ranging from June, '65 - Nov' 71. Concerning financial difficulties with father and commentaries on political and social issues. (Folder folder IV)
  - Miscellaneous - Misc. from friends and associates concerning personal and business matters. (Folder folder V)
  - Literary Correspondence - June '63 - Dec `69 Concerning literary works and advice to or from associates. (Folder folder VI)
  - Personal notes - Commentaries on various of his own works and miscellaneous scribbling. Also commentaries on various authors. (Folder folder VII)
  - Financial Wills Fargo - Bank statements and listing of stocks and-their value. (Folder folder VIII)
  - Financial - stocks Receipts for stocks purchased (Folder folder IX)
  - Financial - income tax - Tax return sheets from 1951 - 1955 (Folder folder X)
  - Financial Miscellaneous - Misc. bank notices and also financial listings. (Folder folder XI)
  - Literary - Misc. Correspondence concerning personal donations and literary [UNK]. (Folder XII)
  - Legal - Ferrari and Swenson. Concerning financial (ie. stocks and bonds) and also family problems. Accounting statements from Mr. [UNK]. (Folder XIII)
  - Literary - Financial and Misc. Correspondence between Dr. Foerster and his publishers and associates. (Folder XIV)
  - Misc. [UNK] greeting cards; notes (Folder XV)